[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software today I'm talking to ziso
they're the senior techn philosopher I
think I got that right at fly.io and the
last time we spoke it was about tail
scale but today we're going to talk
about fly so Z welcome back to software
engineering radio thanks for having me
back it's great to be here the first
thing we should start with is just
defining what fly.io for those who
haven't heard about it so why don't we
start with that fly.io is a way to run
your app as containers across 35 data
centers in one command the same way you
would deploy to one data center you
package your thing up as a Docker
program configure its HTTP Port press
button receive server there's so many
different hosting providers today what
would you say are the the main unique
Parts about fly I know you just touched
on the multiple locations probably the
bgp anyc casting and the private
networking bgp any casting is a
technique that basically lets you use
the entire internet as your load
balancer or you declare you advertise
the same IP range from multiple data
centers and then the public bgp
constellation will just intelligently
route to whichever whichever is the
closest in Internet geography speak for
me all of the stuff goes to the data
center down in toron even though the
Montreal data center is technically
closer bgp is weird and the other big
thing is private networking powered by
wire guard so that all of your internal
traffic between regions is encrypted
over the wire and there's no egress
Charges going from region to region
internally and you were saying how
Montreal was closer to you but it went
to Toronto is there some kind of is it
anycast that's responsible for finding
what it thinks is the shortest or the
quickest path well it's less anycast and
more my ISP figuring out in the bgp bid
which path is the shortest I think that
the connection from where I am in Ottawa
to the monal data center might leave
Bell's Network boundary and I don't know
how Belle's network works internally but
I'd be willing to Guess that crossing a
network boundary is more expensive than
not having to so that's why it's sending
it down to Toronto that's sort of
interesting so it's not even something
that you control it's these isps may
decide to Route this traffic somewhere
that's not necessarily the fastest but
might be cheaper to them yes bgp routing
is an absolute nightmare don't look into
it if you want to sleep well at night
let the experts handle it that's the
Hakuna Matata way to deal with network
engineering Yeah you mentioned really
briefly about connections from region to
region so people who've worked with
hosting Services they're used to let's
say Amazon they have things like vpcs
and ways of creating private networks
what is different about fly's particular
implementation vpcs are very
unopinionated things they let you
basically have any kind of network
topology you want for better and For
Worse the way that fly. I's private
networking differs is that it's very
opinionated it is IPv6 only and you
don't get to control the subnet but it's
in the IPv6 unique local address space
so statistically you're not going to be
interfering with it but you know how
Randomness works I have it set up so
that one of my machines in my home lab
is a router from my other private
network setup to my fly.io private
Network and I can use it to poke things
like my large language model inference
server from basically anywhere without
having to worry about encrypting traffic
on the wire if I understand correctly
your applications themselves don't
necessarily need to encrypt the traffic
when you're doing something from like
your home lab to this instance in fly.
iOS data center because wire guard or
whatever infrastructure you have is
taking care of the encryption yes it
does mean that sometimes you have to
tell applications yes it's okay it's
actually encrypted trust me bro but it
works out a lot better than you'd think
removing problems from the application
layer actually makes your life easier
because it decreases the way that things
can go wrong and makes it easier to tell
where the things went wrong and you've
touched on how any cast allows you to
have a single IP address and routes you
to potential different instances around
the world maybe we can go into the
details of let's say you have an
application and somebody connects to it
maybe you could walk through what the
steps are from there if that makes sense
okay so I'm going to assume that we have
a somewhat cromulent internet connection
that works and is able to resolve Google
so when you make a connection to an
app's IP address your ISP will send you
to one of the data centers and that data
center is running the fly proxy program
I think it's written in Rust the details
don't matter but it'll send it to a data
center that has the fly proxy program
running the fly proxy will look up in
its I think it's a raft store of
information about what IP addresses have
which apps running on weet ports and
then route you to either a random
machine inside your current data center
or a random machine globally or the
nearest one I forget which I forget the
logic I think they changed it recently
but either way it just gets a connection
to a machine somewhere and then proxies
for it and this also means that if you
have a instance of your app running in
Seattle and you are closest to the San
Jose data center your client will
connect to San Jose and then
transparently get wire guard routed to
Seattle the response gets sent back to
San Jose and back to the user this is
all transparent and actually doesn't add
any any latency even though you think it
might and so your application itself
doesn't have to be location where it's
the proxy that's deciding which instance
I do have one of my apps running in all
35 data centers partially as because I
could and partially because I wanted to
see what the challenges were for
operating in an app and that many data
centers and it turned out the challenges
were basically zero and this fly proxy
to someone who's familiar with other
proxies like let's say engine X or ha
proxy think about it as like spicy
opinionated engine X that configures
itself for you there's nothing stopping
you from setting up your own engine X on
top of a fly machine and routing things
that way it's more of the platform does
it for you so you don't need to think
about it you just associate a
certificate with or a domain SL
certificate with an app and you know
you're off to the racis if you go to my
blog zaso Donnet it just automatically
routes you to I think I only have my
blog single homeed and Trana right now I
made some engineering mistakes that make
it hard to go multi- region and okay so
then your application could run without
https because the proxy in front is
doing the TLs termination yep there is a
way to have it do TLS termination
yourself and I think the only reason why
you'd want to do that is Minecraft yeah
pretty sure the only reason You' want to
do that is Minecraft although I don't
remember if Minecraft does TLS
termination anymore I haven't been in
the Minecraft hosting server hosting
scene for like a decade probably not one
of your biggest customers there no
Minecraft is a uniquely Bad Case when it
comes to hosting because it's like Ram
hungry CPU hungry and single thread
performance hungry it sucks everywhere
so are there things that the app needs
to be aware of when it's behind the
proxy because it's like if I create an
application and I assume there's one
instance that my clients are going to
talk to I would think that might be
slightly different than if somebody
talks to my app they may get any number
of instances Are there specific things
you need to account for there in the
case of my website I need to account for
the fact that I have a really weird
combination of a dynamic app and a
static site so like patreon will send
web hooks that will cause it to refresh
the data but it won't send the web hook
to all of the regions it will just send
it to one of them unless I do some
advanced stuff like using fly replay to
shunt the request around like a uh to
basically pass the request around like a
token in a token ring Network to make
sure everything's updated it won't all
get updated at the same time there's
ways I can work around it I just haven't
figured out the clever way to do it yet
yeah cuz an example I was thinking of is
sometimes applications expect you to be
talking to the same instance because you
may have some state in memory or
something like that yeah I am not sure
what the rules are but I imagine that if
if you are in the same TCP session it
would go to the same machine again I
don't know what the rules are I think it
might vary via TCP sessions or atp2
streams or phases of the moon or you
know other goat sacrifice related things
no wait this is networking goat
teleportation related things important
distinction yeah goat teleportation is a
very very underutilized part of chrome
and I think I saw one of the parts of
this proxy is the ability to scale up
and scale down do some form of load
balancing can you kind of explain a
little bit about how that works so the
proxy by itself is fairly dumb it will
just choose a random machine either in
the local data center or close to it but
there's a way to add smarts to it by
using a response header called fly
replay where it allows you to shunt the
request to somewhere else so if you have
a web hook Handler and you want to send
it to a different machine you can reply
with fly replay with machine ID and the
proxy will shunt it over to the other
machine and even wake it up from sleep
if it needs to so you can take a request
you can set up an app such that it gets
a request it uses the machine's API to
find a list of sleeping machines and
then picks one at random shunts the
request over the machine automatically
wakes up handles the thing and then
after about 30 seconds it goes back to
sleep and you get something like they
get something akin to CGI but more fancy
globally distributed with machines so
when you're referring to CGI you're
saying there's some custom code that you
can run in the proxy itself to make this
decision it's not in the proxy itself
it's more that your request hits an app
and then that apps replies instantly
with the fly replay header to tell the
proxy to replay that request somewhere
else oh I see it only works for requests
where the entire HTTP 1.1 form of the
request is 1 Megabyte or less but if you
do it with websockets you can shunt over
the connect request which can allow for
some really interesting things I see so
it's more like you have an API where
your application's own instance has to
recognize that I'm not capable of
handling this request cuz I'm already
too overloaded and you're basically
sending this header back to the proxy so
the proxy knows okay I'm going to spin
up another instance and then either spin
up another instance or like for example
let's say that you are able to detect
unambiguously somehow that a request is
coming from an EU customer and you can
use that to just automatically have the
request get shunted back over to an EU
server so you don't have to deal with
acronym
hell okay this website needs cookies
right uh travel to Berlin or anywhere in
Germany the cookie banners have cookie
banners it's absolutely nuts Oh yeah and
when you go to enough websites in the EU
you will have a mark of cane cookie on
your browser session so that when you go
back to the US you still get the EU
level of cookie
banners yeah just in case right they're
like you were probably maybe you were an
EU citizen so we just want to be sure
but then again like ramen shops in San
Francisco had to worry about gdpr
compliance because they may have gotten
the email address of an EU resident at
one point oh wow yeah it's very
well-intentioned legislation it's just
very wide reaching because computer bad
so let's talk a little bit about the
equivalent of the VMS that people are
running because I know there's a tag
line on your website that says Docker
without Docker Docker is the universal
package format for the internet like
it's pretty safe to say that the best
way to deploy any arbitrary Linux
application to any arbitrary Linux
server is to probably put it into Docker
or something that's compatible with
Docker so in this case fly.io uses
Docker as a package format
and then actually ends up running your
container with a separate Linux kernel
inside firecracker under the hood but
it's basically using the docker image as
a way to encapsulate your app and all of
its dependencies into its own little
jail so that it can't hurt anything or
be affected by anything on the host so
the docker file is this the Primitive
but what you're doing is you're taking
the docker file and creating a VM based
on less the docker file and more the
built Docker image okay yeah it creates
a a micro VM on firecracker and runs it
that way it has all the networking
hooked up to your private Network and
the scary public internet and what's the
difference between a VM you start with
say VMware or Parallels or something
versus these firecracker microv VMS the
main difference is the attack surface a
firecracker microv VM firecracker is a
very opinionated hypervisor it doesn't
have very many devices it doesn't have a
floppy drive it doesn't have a PC
speaker it doesn't have USB firecracker
doesn't even have PCI forwarding support
so it's very small and it allows you to
remove a bunch of stuff that you don't
need from the kernel in order to boot so
that it can boot faster I have seen
things go from the underscore start
symbol in the kernel to the user space
inip tool getting called within about 60
to 120 M seconds hm so is that a
function of them removing all those IO
components and the Parts you wouldn't
need in a server environment yeah there
is a surprising amount of time that is
spent in the kernel in the boot process
and just the kernel starting up that is
waiting for like PCI devices to wake up
or like your Wi-Fi driver to load the
firmware from dis or something it's kind
of remarkable on how long your boot
process ends up spending doing nothing
and then there's cases like that one
recent thing in FreeBSD where people
figured out that they were doing like
driver loading using bubble sort and
they swap that out to merge sword or
something and like boot up to sped up by
like 100 milliseconds and very
complicated cases but yeah less surface
area less bloat more fast although there
is a case where firecracker can't be
used and that's with GPU instances
because you know firecracker doesn't
have PCI pass through and what are gpus
but just opinionated PCI devices with
too much RAM so the GPU instances
they're more traditional VMS just
because of that actually it's basically
the same thing but they use cloud
hypervisor instead of firecracker cloud
hypervisor is a different thing it uses
the virtualization framework KVM but it
allows you to pass through PCI devices
so it still gets most of the same
advantages it's just built by whoever
built that instead of firecracker yes I
believe firecracker was originally built
by AWS for Lambda I don't know the
history of cloud hypervisor but I can't
imagine it's dissimilar and you said the
time to start them is in the hundreds of
milliseconds so that's yeah the thing
that's going to take the longest is your
app starting up and depending on the
stack you can have it be really fast or
really slow I write most of my services
in go and rust so they start faster than
the average one but if you have your app
written in such a way that it opens its
Port as the first thing it'll actually
start getting traffic routed to it
before it's finished starting up and
it'll look faster are there any
tradeoffs between using a full VM I mean
other than the io Parts you mentioned
that are really not relevant for your
use case oh certainly the main intention
with Docker images is that you
crystallize the contents of it once when
the image is being built and then you
never update it ever again with a
traditional VM it is basically a giant
ball of mutable state where that mutable
state is what packages it's running what
kernel it's using and the configuration
of every single on there really what a
microv VM from a Docker container does
is it strips away all of that and gives
you an opinionated floor to build up
from and that opinionated floor is we
will start the command listed in your
Docker file CMD entry and then it is
your problem yeah that really lowers the
potential surface for you where if you
let somebody make a VM they could do
pretty much anything with the VM whereas
with if you force them to provide you a
Docker image you can only do what Docker
has I believe there's a mark file system
as a mutable flag too I haven't had to
use it yet but I believe it does exist
so you can do that and when you do that
I believe it also marks sltm as mutable
for obvious reasons maybe you can talk a
little bit about where these micr VMS
are being hosted my understanding is
you're not a layer on top of a cloud
provider like AWS or or Azure or gcp so
maybe go into what you actually do and
what the thinking was behind that fly.io
purchased Hardware because metal
hardware will always be faster than
having to share CPU time with noisy
neighbors in the cloud so they have
these physical metal hardware and they
are distributed out across the globe in
different data centers I think it's I
don't remember if I'm allowed to say
what data center providers they're using
but if you are so inclined I'm pretty
sure you can look it up from a bgp
Looking Glass I think that might tell it
I don't know I haven't really done
networking stuff since I stopped being
in SRE or at least networking at the bgp
level and it uses epic I think it's at
least the equivalent of Zen 2 but some
of the newer things in the fleet are
zen3 and Zen 4 equivalent but I do know
that the GPU nodes because they're the
newest have the most model number of CPU
and the cores to those when you issue
someone one of these m vmss they just
map one to one you're not sharing the
cores with other users you can choose to
share if you want there's shared cores
and performance cores shared cores are
potentially oversubscribed and
performance cores are very not but
realistically you won't need performance
cores for the P99 of use cases because
most of the time your application is
just just going to sit there doing
nothing anyways yeah I mean I guess a
lot of times applications are stuck in
IO not just stuck in IO but like waiting
for the next request I did some timing
analysis on my website and even when I
was on like the front page of Hacker
News and getting you know thousands of
hits most of the time that was spent by
the application was literally just
waiting for the next request oh because
it processes requests so quickly if
you're thinking about the average web
page that they're not really that CPU
intensive yeah the worst that it has to
do is uncompress something from a zip
file and because of how caches work I
expect that to be basically free I
haven't done the math but I haven't
needed to so and when you're talking
about uncompressing from a zip file like
what's the zip file why is it oh that's
just a sin I made in designing my own
website it serves everything from a zip
file full of gzip streams so I can cheat
interesting okay very specific case then
yeah my website has a lot of interesting
implementation sins that do make it fast
but also make it annoying but do make it
worthy of talking about and it's yours
so you know how it works
supposedly on a good day the servers so
you mentioned how you actually are
buying Hardware is it your staff that's
actually going and racking these things
or is it more you rent some space out at
a Data Center and there's actually
somebody there who takes care of that
sort of thing as far as I understand
it's collocation and remote hands for
the majority of use cases but yeah it's
mostly collocation and remote hands
there's just too many data centers and
too many continents to justify having
staff around every single one of those
data centers it's like 35 data centers
and it's a startup like fly.io does have
people across all those continents but I
don't know the distribution of where
people are that work there versus where
the data centers are and who has
experience in you know Hardware Sr stuff
I would be willing to bet that it's
mostly remote hands yeah that would make
sense I mean there's certainly going to
be cases where you need to buy more
hardware and scale up but it's not going
to be this consistent thing so I would
think you would want some help from the
data center there running a platform
where you are going to get new customers
and you're going to need new hardware I
wonder if you have any insight into I
suppose capacity planning or how much
utilization you're comfortable with
before you're like okay we need to go
buy more things that sort of thing I
don't do most of the capacity planning
stuff I do developer relations or
realistically marketing but I do know
that people are keeping track of what is
being used the most and trying to stay
ahead of the curve with capacity
planning it's just especially difficult
because when you become working at a
startup and you do infra stuff you do
not gain the ability to read people's
minds over the Internet so you know
there's always going to be some level of
nuance and guesswork but I guess part of
my job job is to make their job Harder
by making more users sign up so that
there's more capacity needed so yeah
it's a race you're trying to get them
more customers than they can handle yeah
I'm trying to nerd snipe people just
fast enough that it causes them to need
more capacity but not so fast that it
causes them capacity issues yeah I think
last year or the year before I forget
which I wrote an article about how
before I worked there I wrote an article
about how I thought fly.io was the
reclaimer of heroku's magic and
apparently I caused them capacity issues
so that went well doing my job before I
even had it yeah oh okay this was a blog
post before you worked there there was a
blog post that was written before I
worked there yeah I should probably go
edit it and add that disclaimer that
this was written before I worked there I
probably will after this call they got
that one for free I did get some credits
out of it and those credits basically
paid for my entire fly.io Cloud bills
and I still am writing off of them oh
nice cuz I was thinking as far as the
Capac ftic planning thing I mean I know
that with gpus a lot of companies they
want them right or they want access to
them and so I would imagine that would
be something where you have like a
certain pool and have a big customer
came to you and went like oh we need 200
800s for this period of time you might
be like oh okay uh hold on a moment yeah
the problem with gpus is that they are
backordered for like ages oh my gosh it
is very hard to Source the kind of gpus
that you need in the quantity that you
need in order to keep above the curve it
also doesn't help that a bunch of the
large language models that are getting
released have like 70 billion parameters
and like the size of a language model is
like the parameter count times the
parameter size in bits plus 20% for
inference space it's absolutely just
pure Insanity Nvidia seems determined on
not giving people enough vram like the
machine I'm talking on has a RTX 480 and
that has 16 gigs of vram and sometimes I
feel limited by that like my MacBook Pro
has 64 gigs of RAM Pro tip don't get a
MacBook Pro with 64 gigs of RAM it makes
every time you go into get it serviced
two week wait for them to ship a new
motherboard from China the models just
keep getting bigger but my MacBook can
run llama 370b which is basically gp4
and only had bigger the bigger token
window gpus are really annoying they do
work they're just annoying to Source on
mass one of the selling points that
you've talked about is This Global
deployment of apps but I think you
mentioned that your own website is on a
single region so like what's wrong with
just having a single region and using
CDN and caching I mean that's what I
think a lot of people are used to so
what are the cases where that's not
enough basically when the speed of light
is your limit the speed of light is a
fixed constant and nothing can really go
faster than it like no matter what you
do the speed of light from Northern
Virginia to the EU will always be at
least 125 milliseconds and if those 125
milliseconds matter that's when you'd
scale something out globally but
otherwise you know you don't have to
care Are there specific I suppose
customers or use cases you've seen where
these are examples of where you really
need that yeah a lot of it has to do
with EU customers they want all their
data to be hosted in the for
understandable David of sovereignty
reasons and being able to just put
everything in the EU for them is Trivial
to the point where they don't even need
to bother support to ask how to do it I
know that with Hoku setting up an app in
the EU what meant that it was its own
special type of app and had to have a
different domain name than your main app
and can cause issues and the like but
with fly.io you know you just if an app
is hosted in the EU and you're in
Seattle you just are transparently
routed to the EU behind the scenes and I
suppose in this EU case do you mean that
you would actually be splitting your
database across regions or what would
that look like I'm going to say the
annoying senior software engineer thing
here of it depends because it absolutely
depends on like what database you're
using how you have it set up like how
you do sharding for things that are EU
versus not EU it massively depends but I
believe the platform is flexible enough
to handle what whatever Twisted desires
your heart has of course like you said
it does depend I'm just curious if you
take someone's example of you've got a
web application with a postgress
database my SQL database and you've got
this requirement of I've got customers
in the EU and I've got customers in the
US I'm just kind of curious if you've
seen a specific kind of thing there I
haven't seen a good answer to this and
I'm pretty sure the answer is you can
work around it but it sucks I not sure
what the best option is because like a
lot of the data sovereignty requirements
is newer than most Frameworks have the
ability to handle it and in some cases
just the question of is this user an EU
or us resident is a complicated thing so
I'd imagine that it's a very much a it
depends and you probably have to do some
extensive hacking to your app to get it
to happen but you know that would happen
with any cloud provider and at the very
least with fly.io it allows you to hide
a bit of the Badness because you can
just request things from the EU database
over the private Network and you can
also request things from the North
America database over the private
Network and shunt request around to the
right regions should a US citizen be
requesting something from the EU or vice
versa that's fair so I I suppose you
have The Primitives to decide how you
want to deal with it and mostly because
of the bgp incast component and the
private networking between regions and
the proxy and fly replay working on top
of both yeah one of the posts on your
blog you have a post that's just titled
do I need kubernetes and the
conclusion okay so I am actually working
on a conference talk for devop days
Austin based on the publishing schedule
of this blog this talk will already be
live and on my blog probably and I talk
about how you scale a social network
from a single thing running on a
developer's laptop and a hackathon to
the globe spanning Abomination beyond
all human comprehension and in there I
say that the point where you need
kubernetes is where you are just
slightly more complicated than having
thing multiple things in multiple
regions and you know you can hit the
point with fly.io where you would
probably need kubernetes but that's
where fly.io has your back because
fly.io has a kubernetes instance in it
it uses virtual kuet to translate
kubernetes yaml line noise into fly
machines for you under the hood so that
specific example you gave where you said
you need more than just instances in
multiple regions what are some examples
of things that you need more of more
than like running identical copies of
one Region's deployments in another
region or if you need something more
opinionated like I can only run the
notification provider in the EU for EU
customers or something and a lot of that
could still be implemented on top of
fly.io directly but there's also the
kubernetes provider should you need it
the acronym is FKS and I don't know if
I'm allowed to pronounce it on this
podcast but what you're imagining is the
canonical name that we use all the time
internally I'm kind of anti- kubernetes
and I've played with FKS a bit and I
think that it might make me want to
revise my anti- kubernetes standpoint I
mostly used kubernetes back when
everything was V1 alpha or v0 Alpha all
the amble things were changing
constantly you had to assemble a
production worthy deployment from like
17 beta things that frankly broke way
too often to be reliable in production
like enginex Ingress controller was
still in beta back then and that's like
enginex it was an absolute Nightmare and
it nearly made me burn out of the tech
industry entirely it just kept thinking
that people said this was so much better
and yet like I don't need the
flexibility to be able to handle
scheduling all of the back end stuff for
a Chick-fil-A restaurant or run weapon
systems on an F35 fighter jet like I am
just trying to run a couple HTTP
Services here why is this so hard yeah
and I suppose like you said because you
would only use it if you had these
really specific requirements there's
probably people that jump to it when
they really don't need to yet yeah I
mean in terms of a hammer it is a decent
Hammer kubernetes does get a lot of
things right like not having to require
people to SSH into production to view
logs that already eliminates a huge
class of vulnerabilities from Developers
laptops and npm like the main way that
you apply configuration changes is by
sending a configuration document to the
server and it just figures out the
differences that's huge but it's just
they have these really nice fundamentals
and then everything layered on top of it
just kind of disappoints me I think you
touched on this a little bit but the
kubernetes support in fly.io is not
actually running kubernetes is that
right I believe it runs part of the
control plane it does have a core DNS
container but it's not kubernetes
directly it's virtual kuet which is
something that is basically a thing that
takes the kubernetes API and that allows
you to translate it to whatever calls
under the hood so you can use it to spin
up esxi VMS or like functions as a
service stuff with web assembly or
whatever you want and this is just so
happens to be shimmed to fly machines so
in a way it's similar to the whole
concept of Docker without Docker where
you've got the docker file and the
docker images but you're not running
them using the docker uh runtime
kubernetes s kubernetes yeah yep that's
your next blog post I'll give that idea
to sen you I haven't taken the time to
really dig deep into FKS as much as I
have wanted to because like I have been
busy working on conference talks and I
put effort into it yeah for The Listener
who can't see Z just got a big stack of
papers that looks like it's notes or
drafts for their upcoming conference
stocks so you've worked at not just fly
but before you worked at Heroku so you
have some familiarity with platform as a
service and I was curious from your
perspective what are some challenges of
running one that most developers don't
think about abuse abuse is sometimes
hilarious frankly every so often
somebody sets up a URL shortener and
this just seems to unleash the cracken
when it comes to abuse reports where
you'll get people reporting abuse for a
URL shortener where all it is doing is
this violates our copyright and you're
like how there is a best of abuse
Channel inside the fly.io slack where
you have some of the human rated best
abuse messages we get and occasionally
you find somebody doing something that's
like okay maybe we should actually stop
this but other times you just have the
ongoing war against Bitcoin miners the
war against Bitcoin miners I'm pretty
sure is what killed heroku's free tier
because people discovered that the
Builder machines have slightly faster
CPUs than everything else so they just
spun up a bunch of build things that
were doing Bitcoin mining in the build
step and because we don't live in a
society where we can have all our
dependencies
predeedrum starts up like XM rig or
whatever and CPU mines if you're
wondering if this is at all profitable
for them if they were paying for it no
it would not be but they aren't so yeah
I mean I would think they would have to
open up a lot of accounts to Biblical
numbers yeah cuz even if the build
servers are faster they have to be
mining incredibly slowly yeah CPU mining
is just slow it's a massively parallel
operation and that's why people do it on
gpus or build as6 to do it in Hardware
as fast as they can but it's slow and
then the abuse request you got for the
link shortener that's just because they
make a link shortener on fly that
redirects to something hosted somewhere
else and then you're getting complaints
for the thing that's hosted somewhere
else apparently okay I don't understand
the logic but I'm not paid to yeah so
have you encountered like similar things
with the mining with fly or is it
different because I think you need a
credit card right it is different
because you need a credit card
realistically it slows people down
stolen credit cards can make it easier
but it's an ongoing battle and we seem
to be winning for now it's really
frustrating though because at some level
having a credit card requirement is a
very tight squeeze in the user
acquisition funnel and you know if your
goal is to make the user number line go
up and to the right having that tight
squeeze doesn't help but it's required
because we live in a societ soety the
best way to do it is probably Universal
basic income across the globe that way
people don't need to turn to using
public compute Cloud stuff for mining
Bitcoin it's a problem that might be a
little little too much for a startup to
take on a little bit Yeah so all you can
really do is you know just pluck off the
ones that you see and uh laugh about the
rest yeah in your experience as a
developer Advocate what are the most
common challenges you see people having
like what's bringing them to fly and
then what are they struggling with the
thing that can actually be one of the
most difficult ones is getting people to
understand how cheap it actually is
because the pricing model is somewhat
multi-dimensional and most people
struggle having more than like three
dimensions of something in your head at
once where it's you know by CPU cores
versus the amount of time it's running
versus the amount of memory and
sometimes the amount of persistent disc
that's four dimensions and most most
people can't really comprehend that I've
been thinking about like putting some
examples in there like one of my
projects is something called Ren and
every 12 hours it queries some apis to
get things like the phase of the moon
the current astrological sign three
tarot cards and the current price of
ethereum in United States dollars and it
uses that to make a horoscope about
what's going on using a large language
model hosted on a fly GPU a fly GPU
machine and I priced that out and it was
would cost me about $15 per month in the
worst possible case and I have since
optimized it further by using llama 38b
instead of a mixt old 8 by 7B so it'
probably be down to closer to 10 bucks a
month yeah I think cuz for myself I was
sort of curious for somebody running
something that would require a GPU how
long I suppose it takes to even spin it
up like if it's not running and you need
to start up from cold start is there a
period to even get things running yeah
the good news is that things are fast
enough that the weights should load from
nvme volumes to GPU memory in like
single digit minutes worst case it all
depends on how you're running the model
how the model is loaded what the
bitwidth of the model is because loading
an int4 model into a GPU that doesn't
have in4 in Hardware can be slower
because it has to convert the tensors to
something that GPU can't understand it's
complicated annoying I hate it and
computers are bad but it does work
enough I have found that Llama
37b Or llama 38b at float 16 seems to
load the fastest because gpus natively
have float 16 support yeah and I I
suppose I can see your point about
determining price to be a little bit
difficult because I think one of the
example projects I saw was somebody they
built the equivalent of like a mid
Journey they built this Discord bot yeah
yeah that would spin up a GPU and use
the stable diffusion image generation
model to generate images but looking
from the outside in it wasn't clear to
me if let's say people only used it
every few hours or so how much was I
actually going to be spending and so I
can see how that could be a challenge
yeah my Ren thing uses about two and a
half minutes of GPU time per day which
usually works out well enough since
about to upgrade the model to llama 38b
I can move it to a smaller GPU size
probably a l4s in Seattle and I'm going
to be able to save a fair bit on there
because sometimes with enough GPU node
sleeping or machine sleeping on the same
like server computer box you can run
into a case where you try to request
something and it can't start up because
all the gpus are in use that's a rough
Edge that I know people are working
around it's just
something that has never come up before
because gpus are weirdly sticky and you
can't share gpus between people for
obvious reasons yeah and I suppose the
your use case too is where you know it's
going to be on a daily interval and it
sounds like okay you can predict it's
going to be the three minutes or so and
when it's dependent on user interaction
then it gets a lot more difficult to
predict yeah and that's when you have
like a hot pool of gpus and you spin up
more when you need to and everything's
complicated and it's expensive but
usually by that point you're making
enough money that you can afford to know
figure it out I have been thinking about
using the L 4S's nvenc cores or I think
they're called enven to do video
encoding a bit better than I can on my
CPU at home but I just haven't gotten
around to it yet so I I think maybe the
last thing we should touch on is because
flyes I suppose specialty is on running
globally distributed applications are
there specific use cases or or databases
or software that really works well in
that environment that people should
think about as a tldr if your app
subscribes to the 12 Factor app
philosophy that Heroku published a
decade or so ago you're going to be fine
there is a S3 compatible store called
Tigress that does run on top of fly.io
itself so it can also act as your CDN
for you so you can get that basically
for free as long as you pay for Tigress
which it goes on your fly.io bill in
terms of databases I mean post grass
probably doesn't suck I don't know about
how to scale post grass globally because
I've not been a database Sr I assume
that it's either solvable or you'd use
super base to solve it for you other
databases that might go well valky n RIS
probably would be fine with a valky
cluster or whatever they use for it I
know that there's up stash that has
basically redus that can be used as an
extension running down the list what
else is there either way a lot of the
databases are like they can do it it
probably sucks just about as badly as it
will elsewhere but it won't be like
uniquely bad one other thing I could
think of is that some providers will
have because we were talking about abuse
earlier they'll have a web application
firewall so if somebody's just hammering
your app not to use it but because for
whatever reason they don't like you for
your customers I suppose what are things
you suggest they do in that case most of
the reason why you need a WAFF is if
your compliance people say you need a
WAFF and in that case Cloud flare is
probably fine at this time there's not a
web application firewall built into the
platform but the platform would be a
good place to build such a wff should
you need it to exist especially because
of all of the wire guard networking
means that you can have like your W user
space wire guard connections to Route
traffic to the individual apps so I
suppose the proxy itself I mean is there
anything there that might protect you in
any way I am not sure I could imagine
how you could make a wa with the proxy
they just don't think there's one there
already the as I said the proxy is kind
of dumb mhm and then you mentioned Cloud
flare do you have customers that are
using cdns in combination with what they
have on fly yes the the native CDN via
tigis is very new still so I'd imagine a
lot of existing customers would use
their own CDN stuff either from
cloudflare or like me a bespoke setup
and I recently got rid of the bespoke
setup because it was frankly causing
more problems then it gave me benefits
and I switched it over to tigress and I
haven't been happier because I don't
have to think about it and then those
outside cdns they don't have any issue
with the fact that when they talk to the
proxy you're not really sure where
they're going to be routed right like in
a lot of traditional applications it's
like I know it's talking to Virginia but
in this case yeah I don't know how that
interacts there it's probably one of
those bgp goat teleportation questions I
don't know what's up there I'm assuming
that it's solvable as most things are is
there anything else that you think you
wanted to mention or thought we should
have talked about fly.io does have a
machine API to let you spin up more
compute like opening a faucet to get
more water and that does let you get out
of the way with a lot of fun there's a
lot of fun ways to use the machine's API
when I upload image files from my laptop
to Tigress I actually have something
wired up so it'll spin up a high CPU
High Ram machine just to do the image
conversions upload things to tigress and
then shut down because image conversion
is one of the surprisingly worst cases
for CPU and RAM usage and I have that
wired up as an internal API call for my
CDN named zdn and when other things like
Ren need to upload an image it will send
the image to zdn zdn will spin up the
machine the machine will do the image
conversion upload it to Tigris give a
URL back to zdn which gives it back to
Ren which puts it on the website so that
allows you to like chain stuff together
and be able to get multiple uses out of
things or really like the ideal
spherical cow reading of microservices
architectures so I I suppose the cuz at
the beginning of the conversation we
talked a little bit about how there's
some form of automatic scaling where the
proxy can decide to start instances or
shut them down but this fly machine's
API is is you being able to directly
control when to create and when to shut
them down yes you can find out more at
docs. machines. deev cool so if people
want to learn more about fly or check
out what you're up to cuz I know you
have a really excellent blog where
should they head they should head to
zaso Donnet that is x i a s o. NE or
x-ray Edgar India Alphas Sierra oscar.
net I got them confused because I use
Voice Control software and The Voice
Control software letter for I starts
with the letter s ah okay it's sit for
the letter I and that's going to rewi
yourin
oh yeah don't mess up your hands because
Voice Control software will mess you up
I can't spell anything for my husband
anymore it's great cool well Z thank you
so much for chatting with me thank you
for having me I hope yall listening have
a good day stay hydrated this has been
Jeremy Jung for software engineering
radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at C-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening